Guide to the Connecticut Miscellanea Collection 1721-1999 (Bulk 1906-1936) MS 002 MS 002 MS 002
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Connecticut Miscellanea
1721-1999, (Bulk 1906-1975)
bulk
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Western Connecticut State University. Archives and Special Collections Library
MS 002
1 Linear Feet, 3 boxes
This collection contains historic printed miscellanea of Connecticut. Commercial businesses, municipal boards and commissions, and other clubs and organizations produced the material that is in this collection.
Provenance
Unknown
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains historic printed miscellanea of Connecticut. Printed miscellanea produced for regional promotional purposes may be revealing about the people and the time in which they were produced. Commercial businesses, municipal boards and commissions, and other clubs and organizations produced the material that is in this collection.
This collection is comprised of business pamphlets, programs, newspaper clippings, newsletters, and leaflets. There is also a fragment from the David Scott House in Ridgefield, CT, which is the home of the Ridgefield Historical Society.
Included in this collection are also some issues of The American Hatter (1892-1935) which were originally cataloged separately but are included in this inventory.
Included in the original inventory were NY State line to Bethel, CT. Relocation of U.S. 6 (12 sheets, 2 sets of 6) | 1955; Map of Putnam County, NY. County Superintendent of Highways | 1961; and Ridgefield, Connecticut 2 large maps | 1942-1955, however these items appear to be missing.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged by subject
The files are grouped into 4 series.
Missing Title
General Connecticut Topics
Maps
Military History
Town/City/Area Oriented Materials
Related Material
Truman Warner Papers.
The American Hatter.; Connecticut--Social life and customs.; Hats--Periodicals.; Steam locomotives--United States--Pictorial works.; Bethel (Conn.); Brookfield (Conn.); Guilford (Conn.); Hartford (Conn.); Litchfield (Conn.); New Milford (Conn.); Norwalk (Conn.); Redding (Conn.); Ridgefield (Conn.); Sherman (Conn.); Southbury (Conn.); Wethersfield (Conn.); Wilton (Conn.); Woodbury (Conn.); Clippings.; Fliers (printed matter); Miscellanea.; Publications.; Sketchbooks.
- General Connecticut Topics
  - Connecticut Historical Points of Interest, compiled and published by the Connecticut Chamber of Commerce, ca. 1930 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Old Time Blue Laws by J. R. Randal, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Memorial Dedications, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    General note
    Dedication of the Memorials to Orville Hitchcock Platt and Joseph Roswell Hawley at the State Capital
  - Legislative Research Report, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    Connecticut and New Haven Colony Legislative Session Report covering from 1936 - 1962
  - 4 - H Magazine, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Issues XXIII no. 4, XXII no. 8, XXIV no. 1, XXV no. 1, XXV no. 2, and XXV no. 3 of The Connecticut 4 - H News Magazine
  - The Connecticut Engagement Book, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Suicide Victim J. Henry Roraback, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Connecticut Now and Then, 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    General
    Entire pamphlet of Vol. XXIV No. 3 March 1963; sections of pamphlets Vol.XVII No. 6 June 1957 and Vol. XXI No. 2 February 1960.
    These pamplets were produced by the Connecticut Light and Power Company.
  - Telephone News, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Pamphlet put out by the Southern New England Telephone Company.
  - Postcards, 1907-1933 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    1 postcard of The General Epaphroditis Champion Mansion in East Haddam, 1933.
    1 postcard of the Center Church in Hartford, 1907.
  - American Hatter, 1892-1912 (Box 2-3)
    Contains: v. 37 (#2, 11, 12); v.38 (#3, 4, 10, 11); v. 39 (#2-4); v. 40 (#2); v. 41 (#6, 7, 9)
  - Bailey's Connecticut Marriages by Edwin Webb Wheat, ca. 1930 (Box OS 1)
  - Educational Directory of Connecticut, 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Includes: Ve-po-ad (adding machine); Advanced System for Locating Errors (1894); Arithmetical Detector (1894); Decimplex Improvement (1897); Catholic National Reader: New Primer (1893). Gift of the Longridge Library.
  - Elsie Hill and Mrs. C.L. Robey in Washington, D.C., 1921 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Purchased via eBay, 2017.
  - Party machinery; the caucus and convention system of Connecticut, by Ruth McIntire Dadourian, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Published by the Connecticut League of Women Voters. It was kept inside Mrs. William Allen of Ridgefield's copy of The Actual Government of Connecticut published by the National Woman Suffrage Publishing Co. held by WCSU Special Collections.
  - CL&P's FLOOD recovery story (booklet), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Native American Research Paper Drafts, ca. 1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Papers include "Historic and Prehistoric Indians of the Connecticut Valley" by Agnes Lehning, "Indians of Western Connecticut" by Elaine Hendrickson, and "Indian Land Loss in Virginina: The Beginning of a National Pattern" by Helen C. Rountree.
  - Native American Printed Articles and Pamphlets, 1970-1994 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Acticles and Pamphlets include: "Indians of the Sound: Part II," "Land-Use, Settlement Patterns and Subsistence Agriculture: a demographic perspective," "Guide to Mount Hope," "A Native Thanksgiving: American Indian Cooking," "The Weantinoge Site and an Archeology of Ten Centuries of Native History," "Native American Authors Distribution Project," Faces: the magazine about People "The Iroquois," "Pilgrims' Paradox: Thanksgiving in the eye of the beholder," "Loopholes in Religious Liberty: The Need for a Federal Law to Protext Freedom of Worship for NAtive People," and "New England Logboats: Four Centuries of Watercraft."
  - Weinstein Archeological Dig Photos, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Photographs are from the anthropology 561 summer field school at Sheep Rock that Laurie Weinstein participated in during the summer of 1967.
  - Native American Clippings, 1973-1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Articles include: Cpmmecticut Indians Fight; The Region as Reliquary; book review of "The Colonies in Transition 1660-1713;" Maine Municipalities in Turmoil Over Land Suit Filed by Indians; Hero Falling from Pedestal: Statue of man who led Indian massacre to be moved; 78-man Trive Fights to Keep Its Reservation; Indians Rush to Join Legal Fight for Land; Wampanoags Sow the Seeds of Native Traditions; Indians' Tactics Differ in Bid to Regain Control; New England Indians Strive to Rebuild Tribes; Indians Feel Pull of Past, Realities of Present; Wampanoag Tribe Used to Hunt and Fish All of Cape Cod. Now Their Territory is Limited to a Relatively Small Section of Mashpee; Artifact Hunters Blitz Ancient Indian Sites; Tribe Wants Casino; Flake Makes Digger's Day; The Last of the Mohegans; First Encounters: EArly Thanksgiving Celebrated Peace and Harmony Between Pilgrims and Indians, But the Good Feelings Didn't Last; Blood on Native Soil; Keeping Indian Tradition Is a Family's FAssion; Pequots are Not the Enemy; Bill to Counteract Paugussett Land Claim Passes; Mohegans await the benefits of Recognition; Task Force on Pequot's Land Plans Meets Without Pequots; Chief Tied to Misused Aid; Preserving Tradition and Dispelling Myths; Defining How a Tribe Governs its Land; Tribes closer to reclaiming History; Their Days in the Sun: Mohegans look forward to Regaining Tribal Pride; Indian Gammimg Debate Growing in Intensity; The Siwanoy's Last Stand
- Maps
  - Travels in New England and New York by Timothy Dwight Map Inserts (3 maps, By George Gilbert), 1821 (Folder OS 1.1)
  - William Barker Connecticut Map, 1805 (Folder OS 1, Item 1)
    ~12" x 12"
  - Aerosmith Lewis Connecticut Map, 1804 (Folder OS 1, Item 2)
  - Rhode Island and Connecticut Map, 1835 (Folder OS 1, Item 3)
  - Geographical, Statistical and Historical Map of Connecticut, 1822 (Folder OS 1, Item 4)
    ~20" x 15", Engraved by Young and Delleker
  - H. S. Tanner Connecticut Map, 1839 (Folder OS 2, Item 1)
    ~20" x 15"
  - Colton's Connecticut Map, with portions of New York and Rhode Island, 1855 (Folder OS 2, Item 2)
  - Connecticut; Published by F. Lucas, Baltimore, 1824 (Folder OS 1, Item 5)
  - Fairfield County Facsimile, 1855 (Folder OS 2, Item 3)
    ~20" x 15"; composite
  - Township Map of Massachusetts, Connecticut and Rhode Island, 1857 (Folder OS 8, Item 1)
    ~36" x 24", Published by Ensign, Bridgeman, and Fanning
  - New Map of Connecticut, published by S.D. Tilden, 1873 (Folder OS 8, Item 2)
    ~36" x 24"
  - Connecticut, Engraved by G.W. Boynton, 1838 (Folder OS 8, Item 3)
  - Johnson's Massachusetts, Connecticut, and Rhode Island, 1862 (Folder OS 8, Item 4)
    ~36" x 24", by Johnson and Browning
  - Connecticut State Register and Manual: Senatorial and Congressional Districts and Towns (Map inserts), 1890-1919 (Folder OS 3)
    Maps included are from the years: 1890-1891; 1898-1912; 1914-1917; 1919.
  - Connecticut State Register and Manual: CT Map inserts, 1898-1932 (Folder OS 4)
    Maps range in date from 1898-1932; the following years have no maps: 1904, 1913-1915, 1916-1917, 1925, 1930.
  - Connecticut State Register and Manual: CT Map inserts, 1898-1932 (Folder OS 5)
  - Map of the Railroads of Connecticut by W.H. Dodd and Co., Hartford, 1894 (Folder OS 10, Item 1)
  - General History of Connecticut Map, by D. Clark and Co., 1829 (Folder OS 10, Item 2)
    Items listed are taken from books in the collection. The title and the call number of the book that the map is taken from is listed below.
    F104.F2 J32 1932 - History and genealogy of the families of old Fairfield
    F104.H357 H375 1899 - Hartford in history: a series of papers / by resident authors
    F104.H45 H4 1910 - Hebron, Connecticut, bicentennial, August 23d to 25th, 1908: an account of the celebration of the two hundredth anniversary of the incorporation of the town: 1708-1908
    F104.N662 N4 - Report of the Committee Appointed to Inquire into the Condition of the New Haven Burying Ground: and to propose a plan for its improvement
    F104.N53 N55 - The New Canaan Historical Society annual
    F104 N78 B6 1945 - Newtown: 1708-1758: historical notes and maps (2 maps)
    F104.S5 C36 1902 - Seymour, past and present (2 maps)
  - Fairfield Ancient and Modern, by Reon B. Roberts, 1932 (Folder OS 6, Item 1)
  - [Map of Newtown], By John Neville Boyle, 2 pages, 1945 (Folder OS 6, Item 2)
  - Town of New Canaan 1945 Facsimile and Canaan Parish Maps 1945 Facsimile, ca. 1772; , ca.1860 (Folder OS 6, Item 3)
  - Hartford Connecticut based on Nathaniel Goodwin's 1824 Survey, 1899 (Folder OS 7, Item 1)
  - Town of Hebron, drawn by Isaac Pinney 1744, 1908 (Folder OS 7, Item 2)
  - Plan of the Burial Ground, New Haven Connecticut, 1839 (Folder OS 7, Item 3)
    F104.S5 C36 1902 - Seymour, past and present (2 maps), Gift of Brooklyn Historical Society
    F104.N662 N4 - Report of the Committee Appointed to Inquire into the Condition of the New Haven Burying Ground: and to propose a plan for its improvement, Gift of Brooklyn Historical Society
  - U.S. Geological Survey Connecticut Derby Sheet, 1889, and Map of Seymour, published by Matthews-Northrup Works, 1902 (Folder OS 7, Item 4)
    Gift of Brooklyn Historical Society
  - Official Map of Connecticut, Pubished by the Highway State Department, 1959 (Folder OS 11, Item 1)
  - Official Map of Connecticut, Pubished by the Highway State Department, 1958 (Folder OS 11, Item 2)
  - Connecticut Turnpike, 1958 (Folder OS 11, Item 3)
    F91 .C65 no.46 1935 - Forty years of highway development in Connecticut, 1895-1935
  - Map of Connecticut: Showing the System of State Highways and Other Improved Roads, 1935 (Folder OS 11, Item 4)
    F 100 .F45 1938 - Connecticut; a guide to its roads, lore, and people, written by workers of the Federal writers' project of the Works progress administration for the state of Connecticut; Gift of Brooklyn Historical SocietyF91 .C65 no.46 1935 - Forty years of highway development in Connecticut, 1895-1935
  - Works Progress Administration, Federal Writer's Project, 1938 (Folder OS 11, Item 5)
    F 100 .F45 1938 - Connecticut; a guide to its roads, lore, and people, written by workers of the Federal writers' project of the Works progress administration for the state of Connecticut; Gift of Brooklyn Historical Society
  - Highway Picnic Areas, Published by Connecticut State Highway Department, 1958 (Folder OS 11, Item 6)
  - Highway Picnic Areas, Published by Connecticut State Highway Department, 1955 (Folder OS 11, Item 7)
  - Map of Newtown Connecticut, published by the Newtown Real Estate Board, 1958 (Folder OS 11, Item 8)
  - Bicentennial Issue Map of Connecticut, 1975-1976 (Folder OS 11, Item 9)
  - Vacation Guide Showing Points of Interest in Northwestern Connecticut, 1957 (Folder OS 11, Item 10)
  - Glacial Geography of Connecticut, 1930 (Folder OS 9)
  - Geological map of Long & Staten islands with the environs of New York, and Geological Map of the Middle and Middle Western States (NJ-IL), removed from the Geology of New York, 1840 (Folder OS 12, Item 1-2)
    Both maps are hand colored. The Long Island map is 52".
- Military History
  - Second Regiment: CT Volunteer Heavy Artillery, 1862-1865, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Fifteenth Regiment: CT Volunteers, 1862-1865, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sixteenth Regiment: CT Volunteers, 1862-1865, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Seventeenth Regiment: CT Volunteers, 1862- 1865, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - State of Connecticut Adjutant General's Office "Errata Record of Connecticut Men in the war of Rebellion (1861-1865); Spanish-American War, Philippine Insurrection, and China Relief Expedition (1898-1904)," January 1, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Military Museum of Southern New England (Danbury, CT), 1992-1999 (Box 1, Folder 22-23)
  - Illustrated Memoir of the World War, 1930 (Box OS 1, Item 5)
    Donated in 2018 by Gerald and Roseanne Shea.
    Published in New Haven for the AEF Veterans.
- Town/City/Area Oriented Materials
  - Bethel publications, etc., 1959-1978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    History of a Yankee Church, 1959 History of the Bethel Volunteer Fire Department, 1831-1978, 1928 Bethel, Connecticut, Centennial 1855-1955, 1955
  - Bridgeport, 1930, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1.1)
    Purchased via ebay, Feb 2017
    Two AP photos of Jasper McLevy, first Socialist Mayor of Bridgeport.
  - Brookfield publications, etc., 1957 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    The Venerable House: The Congregational Church of Brookfield, Connecticut, 1957
  - Guilford publications, etc., undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Historical Papers Relating to the Henry Whitfield
    House Guilford, CT.
  - Hartford publications, etc., 1906-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Hartford: A City a Tour with Heritage Trails, 1996
    Souvenir of Hartford, 1906
  - Bancroft, George. Address at Hartford, Before the Delegates to the Democratic Convention of the Young Men of Connecticut, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Unbound, some foxing.
  - Litchfield publications, etc., 1954 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    The Lure of Litchfield, June 1954
  - New Milford publications, etc., 1907 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    200th Anniversary of the Settlement of the Town of New Milford, June 17, 1907
  - Norwalk publications, etc., 1894; , 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    New Canaan Paper, "Burning of Norwalk," July 21, 1894
  - Redding publications, etc., 1956; , 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Program, Redding Bicentennial Ridgefield:
    Brochure: Putnam Memorial At Redding Conn. A State Park, 1956
    Putnam Memorial brochure donated by George Combs, 2013.
  - Ridgefield Publications, etc., 1935-1999 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Ridgefield Historical Society David Scott House Keepsake Fragment, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    David Scott House keepsake fragment (ca 1713)
  - Sherman publications, etc., 1940-1953 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Giddings, Allie H. Our Sherman School-Its Heritage and Progress" (ca. 1940)
    Giddings, Town of Sherman, 1802: 150 Years of Sherman Life, 1952
    Giddings, A History of the Sherman Church, August 1953
  - Southbury publications, etc., 1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Southbury, Connecticut: Our Town, January 1962
  - Wethersfield publications, etc., 1932 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Washington Bicentennial Celebration, June 7, 1932
  - Wilton publications, etc., 1900 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Wilton Parish, 1726-1800, 1900
  - Woodbury publications, etc., 1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Ancient Woodbury Tercentenary, July 4-5, 1959
  - Henry L. Pike, Jr. Locomotive Sketchbook [Jan. 3rd 1866]. (Box OS Box 1, Item 1)
    Pencil Sketches of steam locomotives from various railroads in the northeast U.S.. Sketches are presumably a catalog to sell reproductions (framed and unframed) of these drawings.
  - The Ridgefield Press, Diamond Jubilee Issue, 1875-1950 (Box OS Box 1, Item 2)
  - Ridgefield Today, 275 Years of History and Tradition; The News-Times, Thursday, September 22, 1983. (Box OS Box 1, Item 3)
  - Calendar from Terry Lumber Company, Bethel, CT, 1950 (Box OS Box 1, Item 4)
  - Welcome and Real Estate Guides, ca. 1990 (Box 2, Folder 1-11)
    Includes guides for: Norwalk, Westport-Weston (x2), Ridgefield (x2), New Canaan (x2), Newtown (x2), Fairfield (x2), Greenwich (x2), Bethel, New Milford (x2), Darien, Danbury (x6)